start doing jobs, we don't have to do them anymore, and we get freed up from drudgery and toil. Now, when I talk about this with my friends in Cambridge and Silicon Valley, they say, "Fantastic. No more drudgery, no more toil. This gives us the chance to imagine an entirely different kind of society, a society where the creators and the discoverers and the performers and the innovators come together with their patrons and their financiers to talk about issues, entertain, enlighten, provoke each other." It's a society really, that looks a lot like the TED Conference. And there's actually a huge amount of truth here. We are seeing an amazing flourishing taking place. In a world where it is just about as easy to generate an object as it is to print a document, we have amazing new possibilities. The people who used to be craftsmen and hobbyists are now makers, and they're responsible for massive amounts of innovation. And artists who were formerly constrained can now do things that were never, ever possible for them before. So this is a time of great flourishing, and the more I look around, the more convinced I become that this quote, from the physicist Freeman Dyson, is not hyperbole at all. This is just a plain statement of the facts. We are in the middle of an astonishing period. ["Technology is a gift of God. After the gift of life it is perhaps the greatest of God's gifts. It is the mother of civilizations, of arts and of sciences." — Freeman Dyson] Which brings up another great question: What could possibly go wrong in this new machine age? Right? Great, hang up, flourish, go home. We're going to face two really thorny sets of challenges as we head deeper into the future that we're creating. The first are economic, and they're really nicely summarized in an apocryphal story about a back-and-forth between Henry Ford II and Walter Reuther, who was the head of the auto workers union. They were touring one of the new modern factories, and Ford playfully turns to Reuther and says, "Hey Walter, how are you going to get these robots to pay union dues?" And Reuther shoots back, "Hey Henry, how are you going to get them to buy cars?" Reuther's problem in that anecdote is that it is tough to offer your labor to an economy that's full of machines, and we see this very clearly in the statistics. If you look over the past couple decades at the returns to capital -- in other words, corporate profits -- we see them going up, and we see that they're now at an all-time high. If we look at the returns to labor, in other words total wages paid out in the economy, we see them at an all-time low and heading very quickly in the opposite direction. So this is clearly bad news for Reuther. It looks like it might be great news for Ford, but it's actually not. If you want to sell huge volumes of somewhat expensive goods to people, you really want a large, stable, prosperous middle class. We have had one of those in America for just about the entire postwar period. But the middle class is clearly under huge threat right now. We all know a lot of the statistics, but just to repeat one of them, median income in America has actually gone down over the past 15 years, and we're in danger of getting trapped in some vicious cycle where inequality and polarization continue to go up over time. The societal challenges that come along with that kind of inequality deserve some attention. There are a set of societal challenges that I'm actually not that worried about, and they're captured by images like this. This is not the kind of societal problem that I am concerned about. There is no shortage of dystopian visions about what happens when our machines become self-aware, and they decide to rise up and coordinate attacks against us. I'm going to start worrying about those the day my computer becomes aware of my printer. (Laughter) (Applause) So this is not the set of challenges we really need to worry about. To tell you the kinds of societal challenges that are going to come up in the new machine age, I want to tell a story about two stereotypical American workers. And to make them really stereotypical, let's make them both white guys. And the first one is a college-educated professional, creative type, manager, engineer, doctor, lawyer, that kind of worker. We're going to call him "Ted." He's at the top of the American middle class. His counterpart is not college-educated and works as a laborer, works as a clerk, does low-level white collar or blue collar work in the economy. We're going to call that guy "Bill." And if you go back about 50 years, Bill and Ted were leading remarkably similar lives. For example, in 1960 they were both very likely to have full-time jobs, working at least 40 hours a week. But as the social researcher Charles Murray has documented, as we started to automate the economy, and 1960 is just about when computers started to be used by businesses, as we started to progressively inject technology and automation and digital stuff into the economy, the fortunes of Bill and Ted diverged a lot. Over this time frame, Ted has continued to hold a full-time job. Bill hasn't. In many cases, Bill has left the economy entirely, and Ted very rarely has. Over time, Ted's marriage has stayed quite happy. Bill's hasn't. And Ted's kids have grown up in a two-parent home, while Bill's absolutely have not over time. Other ways that Bill is dropping out of society? He's decreased his voting in presidential elections, and he's started to go to prison a lot more often. So I cannot tell a happy story about these social trends, and they don't show any signs of reversing themselves. They're also true no matter which ethnic group or demographic group we look at, and they're actually getting so severe that they're in danger of overwhelming even the amazing progress we made with the Civil Rights Movement. And what my friends in Silicon Valley and Cambridge are overlooking is that they're Ted. They're living these amazingly busy, productive lives, and they've got all the benefits to show from that, while Bill is leading a very different life. They're actually both proof of how right Voltaire was when he talked about the benefits of work, and the fact that it saves us from not one but three great evils. ["Work saves a man from three great evils: boredom, vice and need." — Voltaire] So with these challenges, what do we do about them? The economic playbook is surprisingly clear, surprisingly straightforward, in the short term especially. The robots are not going to take all of our jobs in the next year or two, so the classic Econ 101 playbook is going to work just fine: Encourage entrepreneurship, double down on infrastructure, and make sure we're turning out people from our educational system with the appropriate skills. But over the longer term, if we are moving into an economy that's heavy on technology and light on labor, and we are, then we have to consider some more radical interventions, for example, something like a guaranteed minimum income. Now, that's probably making some folk in this room uncomfortable, because that idea is associated with the extreme left wing and with fairly radical schemes for redistributing wealth. I did a little bit of research on this notion, and it might calm some folk down to know that the idea of a net guaranteed minimum income has been championed by those frothing-at-the-mouth socialists Friedrich Hayek, Richard Nixon and Milton Friedman. And if you find yourself worried that something like a guaranteed income is going to stifle our drive to succeed and make us kind of complacent, you might be interested to know that social mobility, one of the things we really pride ourselves on in the United States, is now lower than it is in the northern European countries that have these very generous social safety nets. So the economic playbook is actually pretty straightforward. The societal one is a lot more challenging. I don't know what the playbook is for getting Bill to engage and stay engaged throughout life. I do know that education is a huge part of it. I witnessed this firsthand. I was a Montessori kid for the first few years of my education, and what that education taught me is that the world is an interesting place and my job is to go explore it. The school stopped in third grade, so then I entered the public school system, and it felt like I had been sent to the Gulag. With the benefit of hindsight, I now know the job was to prepare me for life as a clerk or a laborer, but at the time it felt like the job was to kind of bore me into some submission with what was going on around me. We have to do better than this. We cannot keep turning out Bills. So we see some green shoots that things are getting better. We see technology deeply impacting education and engaging people, from our youngest learners up to our oldest ones. We see very prominent business voices telling us we need to rethink some of the things that we've been holding dear for a while. And we see very serious and sustained and data-driven efforts to understand how to intervene in some of the most troubled communities that we have. So the green shoots are out there. I don't want to pretend for a minute that what we have is going to be enough. We're facing very tough challenges. To give just one example, there are about five million Americans who have been unemployed for at least six months. We're not going to fix things for them by sending them back to Montessori. And my biggest worry is that we're creating a world where we're going to have glittering technologies embedded in kind of a shabby society and supported by an economy that generates inequality instead of opportunity. But I actually don't think that's what we're going to do. I think we're going to do something a lot better for one very straightforward reason: The facts are getting out there. The realities of this new machine age and the change in the economy are becoming more widely known. If we wanted to accelerate that process, we could do things like have our best economists and policymakers play "Jeopardy!" against Watson. We could send Congress on an autonomous car road trip. And if we do enough of these kinds of things, the awareness is going to sink in that things are going to be different. And then we're off to the races, because I don't believe for a second that we have forgotten how to solve tough challenges or that we have become too apathetic or hard-hearted to even try. I started my talk with quotes from wordsmiths who were separated by an ocean and a century. Let me end it with words from politicians who were similarly distant. Winston Churchill came to my home of MIT in 1949, and he said, "If we are to bring the broad masses of the people in every land to the table of abundance, it can only be by the tireless improvement of all of our means of technical production." Abraham Lincoln realized there was one other ingredient. He said, "I am a firm believer in the people. If given the truth, they can be depended upon to meet any national crisis. The great point is to give them the plain facts." So the optimistic note, great point that I want to leave you with is that the plain facts of the machine age are becoming clear, and I have every confidence that we're going to use them to chart a good course into the challenging, abundant economy that we're creating. Thank you very much. (Applause)
commenceront à travailler, nous n'aurons plus besoin de le faire, ce qui nous libérera des corvées et des durs labeurs. Quand je parle de ça avec mes amis à Cambridge et à Silicon Valley, ils disent : « Génial. Plus de corvées, plus de durs labeurs. Ça nous donne la possibilité d'imaginer une société entièrement différente, une société où les créateurs, découvreurs, acteurs et innovateurs se réunissent avec leurs clients et leurs bailleurs de fonds pour évoquer et envisager divers sujets, s'inspirer mutuellement et confronter leurs idées. » Une société qui, dans le fond, ressemble beaucoup à une conférence TED. Et il y a en ça une grande part de vérité. Nous voyons une incroyable éclosion prendre forme. Dans un monde où générer un objet est tout aussi facile que d'imprimer un document, les possibilités qui s'offrent à nous sont fascinantes. Ceux qui étaient naguère des artisans et des amateurs sont de nos jours des concepteurs et ont à leur actif des tonnes d'innovations. Des artistes qui se sentaient limités peuvent maintenant faire des choses qui ne leur avaient jamais été possibles auparavant. Nous sommes donc dans une période florissante. Et plus j'observe, plus je suis convaincu que cette citation du physicien Freeman Dyson n'est pas hyperbolique du tout. Il s'agit là d'un constat. Nous vivons au cours d'une période fascinante. Ce qui soulève une autre grande question : qu'est-ce qui pourrait bien mal tourner dans cette nouvelle ère des machines ? Hein ? Persévère, prospère, puis rentre à la maison. Nous allons faire face à deux séries de défis particulièrement épineux à mesure que nous nous enfonçons dans le futur que nous sommes en train de créer. Les premiers sont d'ordre économique et joliment résumés par un échange apocryphe entre Henry Ford II et Walter Reuther, qui était à la tête du syndicat des ouvriers de l'automobile. Alors qu'ils faisaient la tournée des nouvelles usines modernes Ford, se tourna vers Reuther et lui dit d'un air jovial : « Hé Walter, comment tu vas t'y prendre pour faire payer les cotisations syndicales à ces robots ? » Et Reuther réplique : « Hé Henry, comment tu vas t'y prendre pour leur faire acheter des voitures ? » Le problème de Reuther dans cette anecdote est qu'il est difficile de proposer sa force de travail dans une économie pleine de machines, et c'est clairement se que disent les statistiques. Si on regarde les dernières décennies, le retour sur capital, -- c'est-à-dire les profits des entreprises, a augmenté. Et on voit qu'il est maintenant à son plus haut niveau jamais atteint. Si on regarde le retour sur travail, c'est à dire le total des salaires dans l'économie, on voit qu'il se trouve à son niveau le plus bas et qu'il continue à dégringoler à vive allure. C'est clairement une mauvaise nouvelle pour Reuther. On pourrait croire que c'est une bonne nouvelle pour Ford, mais en fait non. Si on veut vendre de grandes quantités de marchandises relativement chères, ce qu'il faut c'est une classe moyenne large, stable et prospère. Nous avons connu cela en Amérique pendant presque toute la période d'après-guerre. Mais la classe moyenne fait aujourd'hui face à une grande menace. Nous avons tous la tête pleine de ces statistiques, mais je vais en reprendre juste une : le revenu médian en Amérique a baissé sur les 15 dernières années, et nous courrons le risque de tomber dans un cercle vicieux où l'inégalité et la polarisation continuent à s'accroître avec le temps. Les phénomènes de société qui accompagnent ce genre d'inégalités méritent notre attention. Il s'agit d'une série de changements de société qui ne me préoccupent pas tant que ça et que des images comme celle-ci rendent bien. Ce n'est pas le genre de problèmes de société qui me préoccupe. Les dystopies sur ce qui se passera quand nos machines deviendront conscientes et décideront de se soulever et de nous attaquer ne manquent pas. Je commencerai à me faire du souci là-dessus le jour où mon ordinateur reconnaîtra mon imprimante. (Rires) (Applaudissements) Il ne s'agit donc pas des défis dont nous devons nous soucier. Pour vous aborder les défis de société auxquels nous serons confrontés dans la nouvelle ère des machines, je vais vous raconter une histoire sur deux travailleurs américains typiques. Pour en faire de vrais stéréotypes, disons qu'ils sont tous les deux blancs. Le premier a un diplôme universitaire, il est du type créatif, du genre manager, ingénieur, docteur, avocat... ce genre-là. On va l'appeler Ted. Il représente le haut de la classe moyenne américaine. L'autre n'a pas de diplôme universitaire, il est ouvrier, employé de bureau, a un emploi dans un secteur tertiaire de bas-niveau ou secondaire. On va appeler ce gars-là Bill. Si vous remontez 50 ans en arrière, Bill et Ted menaient des vies remarquablement semblables. Par exemple, en 1960, ils avaient tous les deux toutes les chances d'avoir un emploi à plein temps, d'au moins 40 heures par semaine. Mais comme l'a démontré, documents à l'appui, le sociologue Charles Murray, à mesure que nous avons automatisé l'économie, et 1960 n'est que le point de départ de l'utilisation des ordinateurs par les entreprises, à mesure que nous avons commencé à injecter progressivement de la technologie, des automates et des outils numériques dans l'économie, le sort de Bill et celui de Ted ont beaucoup divergé. Sur toute cette échelle de temps, Ted a gardé un emploi à plein temps. Mais pas Bill. Dans de nombreux cas, Bill a entièrement disparu de l'économie, alors que Ted presque jamais. Avec le temps, le couple de Ted a bien tenu. Pas celui de Bill. Les enfants de Ted ont grandi dans un foyer à deux parents, alors que ceux de Bill, tout au contraire, à mesure qu'on avance dans le temps. D'autres formes d'exclusion sociale de Bill ? Son abstention aux élections présidentielles a augmenté, et il a commencé à aller en prison bien plus souvent. Je ne peux pas raconter une histoire heureuse sur ces tendances sociales de même qu'elles ne montrent aucun signe d'inversion. Elles restent vraies quel que soit le groupe ethnique ou démographique observé, et elles prennent une telle ampleur qu'elles risquent même d'effacer les incroyables progrès réalisés grâce au mouvement des droits civiques. Ce que mes amis à Silicon Valley et à Cambridge refusent de voir c'est qu'ils sont Ted. Ils vivent une vie pleine, épatante, productive, avec tous les avantages qui vont avec, alors que Bill lui mène une vie bien différente. Tous deux démontrent que Voltaire ne s'était pas trompé lorsqu'il parlait des bénéfices du travail et du fait qu'il nous éloigne non pas d'un mais de trois grands maux. [« Le travail éloigne de nous trois grands maux : l'ennui, le vice et le besoin. »] Ces défis, qu'est-ce qu'on en fait ? Le scénario économique est étonnamment clair là-dessus, étonnamment direct, et encore plus catégorique à court terme. Les robots ne vont pas nous voler tous nos emplois dans les deux ans à venir, donc la théorie économique classique suffira à : encourager l'entrepreneuriat, doubler la mise sur les infrastructures et s'assurer que notre système éducatif produise des individus avec les compétences appropriées. Mais sur le long terme, si on se dirige vers une économie à haute teneur en technologie et faible teneur en force de travail, comme c'est le cas, alors il nous faut envisager des interventions plus radicales, par exemple, quelque chose comme un revenu minimum garanti. Certains dans cette pièce pourraient se sentir mal à l'aise en entendant ça, parce que cette idée est associée à l'extrême gauche et à des programmes de redistribution des richesses plutôt radicaux. Je me suis penché sur cette notion et ça pourrait calmer certains esprits de savoir que l'idée d'un revenu net minimum garanti a été défendue par ces socialistes enragés que sont Friedrich Hayek, Richard Nixon et Milton Friedman. Et si vous en venez à vous faire du souci en pensant qu'un tel revenu garanti pourrait nous enlever l'envie de réussir et nous rendre fainéants, vous serez peut-être curieux d'entendre que la mobilité sociale, une des choses qui fait notre fierté aux Etats-Unis, est aujourd'hui inférieure à ce qu'elle est dans les pays d'Europe du Nord qui ont ces minima sociaux si généreux. Le scénario économique est bien simple et direct. Celui qui traite de la société pose bien plus de questions. Je ne sais pas quel scénario peut donner à Bill l'opportunité de trouver un emploi et de le conserver toute sa vie. Ce que je sais c'est que l'éducation joue un grand rôle. J'en ai fait l'expérience moi-même. J'ai été un enfant Montessori pendant les premières années de ma scolarité, et ce que cette éducation m'a appris c'est que le monde est un lieu intéressant et que mon rôle est de l'explorer. L'école s'arrêtait à la troisième année, alors je suis entré dans le système éducatif public et j'ai eu l'impression d'être envoyé au goulag. Avec le recul, je sais que le but était de me préparer à une vie d'employé de bureau ou d'ouvrier, mais à l'époque j'avais l'impression que le but était de me noyer d'ennui jusqu'à ce que je me fonde dans le moule. Nous devons faire mieux que ça. Nous ne pouvons pas continuer à produire des Bill. Nous voyons les prémisses d'une amélioration. Nous voyons l'impact profond que la technologie a sur l'éducation et sur le recrutement du personnel, du plus bas au plus haut niveau d'instruction. Nous entendons les voix de milieux d'affaires à succès nous dire que nous devons repenser certaines des choses qui nous tiennent le plus à cœur. Et ce à quoi l'on assiste, est le déploiement d’efforts soutenus et sérieux, afin de trouver, grâce aux données disponibles, le moyen d'intervenir auprès de certaines de nos populations les plus sensibles. Les signes encourageants sont donc là. Je ne veux pas avoir l'air de dire, ne serait-ce qu'un instant, que ce que nous avons suffira. Nous sommes confrontés à des défis de taille. Pour donner un seul exemple, il y a environ 5 millions d'Américains. qui sont au chômage depuis au moins six mois. Nous n'arriverons pas à régler leurs problèmes en les renvoyant au Montessori. Et ma plus grosse préoccupation, est que nous créions un monde regorgeant de technologies reluisantes, mais incorporées dans une société vétuste, soutenue par une économie qui génère de l'inégalité au lieu de générer des opportunités. Mais en réalité je ne crois pas que nous allons faire ça. Je crois que nous allons faire bien mieux pour une raison très simple : ces choses commencent à se savoir. Les réalités de cette nouvelle ère des machines et les changement économiques commencent à mieux être compris. Si on voulait accélérer le processus, on pourrait par exemple opposer nos meilleurs économistes et dirigeants à Watson au « Jeopardy ». On pourrait envoyer le Parlement en voyage à bord d'une voiture automate. Si on faisait assez de choses comme ça, on parviendrait à ancrer dans l'esprit des gens que les choses vont changer. Et dés lors, tout est possible, car je ne crois pas un instant que nous ayons oublié comment surmonter des défis de taille, ou que nous soyons devenus trop apathiques ou insensibles pour nous y mettre. J'ai commencé ma présentation par des citations de gens de lettres que séparent un océan et un siècle. Je finirai, si vous le permettez, par les mots d'hommes politiques tout aussi distants. Winston Churchill est venu au MIT, mon foyer, en 1949 et a dit : « Si vous devons amener les masses du peuple de chaque terre à la table de l'abondance, ce ne sera que par l'amélioration incessante de tous nos moyens techniques de production. » Abraham Lincoln s'était rendu compte qu'il y avait un autre ingrédient. Il a dit : « J'ai une grande confiance dans le peuple. Si la vérité lui est donnée, on peut lui faire confiance pour surmonter n'importe quelle crise nationale. L'essentiel est de lui présenter les faits tels qu'ils sont. » La note optimiste, essentiel sur laquelle je vous quitterai, est que les faits concernant l'ère des machines apparaissent de plus en plus tels qu'ils sont et j'ai toute confiance de croire que nous les utiliserons pour nous guider à bon port dans l'économie d'exigence et d'abondance que nous sommes en train de créer. Merci beaucoup. (Applaudissements)